Federico Fabio Frattini

⊠: federico.frattini@feem.it **У**: @FedFabFrat □: +393757215672 **(b)**: Personal Website **in**: Linkedin Profile

I am a Researcher at the Fondazione Eni Enrico Mattei, where I am working on research projects related to the labour and political economics of the green transitions. I am also completing a PhD in Economics at Trinity College Dublin, where I am working on research projects related to political economics and the economics of crime. I am passionate about coding, programming languages and statistical software. I am curious, a hard worker, with an analytical mindset prone to problem-solving.

Education

Ph.D., Economics, Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 - (Expected) March 2022

Thesis title: "Essays in Political Economics"

Supervisor: Nicola Mastrorocco

M.Sc., Economics, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2015-2017

Supervisor: Massimo Bordignon

B.Sc., Economics and Management, Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, 2011-2015

Supervisor: Salvatore Piccolo

Work Experience

Fondazione Eni Enrico Mattei, September 2022 - Present

- Researcher:
 - · Labour in the Low-carbon Transition (LiLT) unit.

Trinity College Dublin, September 2018 - August 2022

- Guest lecturer:
 - · Workshop in Big Data and Machine Learning (M.Sc., Ph.D.) at Maynooth University, Spring 2022.
- Teaching Assistant:
 - Introduction to Microeconomics (M.Sc.), Fall 2021, val.: 5/5. Topics in Political Economy (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, 2020, val.: 4.75/5.
 - · Development Economics (M.Sc.), Spring 2020. · Emergence of Macroeconomic Policy (M.Sc.), Spring 2020, val.: 4.3/5.
 - · Long Run Development (M.Sc.), Fall 2019, val.: 5/5. · Introduction to Economic Policy A/B (B.Sc.), 2018-2019, val.: 4.11/5.
- Research Assistant.

SAS, May 2018 - August 2018

• Training Analytical Consultant: Organizing and delivering classes on SAS Base programming language.

Skills, Technologies and Languages

Research Skills:

· Data management. · Data scraping. · Data visualization. · Micro-Econometrics. Causal inference. · Machine Learning.

Software: STATA, Python, R, SQL, QGIS, SAS, Office.

Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent).

Research Projects

Setting an example: political leaders' cues and health behavior in the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic in Mexico, with Bruno Morando and Luciano Ayala, Latin American Policy (2021)

Abstract: How do political leaders' cues affect citizen behavior regarding a new and complex issue? We address this question

in the context of the early stages of the Covid-19 pandemic in Mexico, using electoral outcomes and municipal-level mobility data from Facebook's Movement Range Maps. In March 2020, Mexico's president downplayed constantly the severity of the coming health crisis by continuing his political rallies throughout the country and encouraging people to leave their homes. Using an event-study analysis, we find that, after the first press conference where his government declared mobility restrictions were not yet necessary, on March 13, citizens' geographic mobility in pro-government municipalities was higher than in cities where support for the president was less strong. Our results are robust to several specifications and definitions of political support. Moreover, we find evidence that our results are driven by cities with higher media penetration, which implies that they can be attributed to people's reactions to the president's cues rather than to systematic differences in the preferences of his supporters.

Simultaneous elections and electoral outcomes: evidence from Italy

Abstract: This paper investigates the impact that the simultaneity of national and local elections has on the local electoral stage, in terms of civic and political participation, political competition and electoral results. Methodologically, I employ a difference-in-differences design that exploits the staggered nature of the local elections in Italy, where some municipalities experience the simultaneity, while the rest do not. Voters' participation is positively impacted, with homogeneous effects along the gender dimension. Political participation mildly increases, while its competition is affected in an opposite way. Mayors winning in this simultaneous setting are more likely to have previous office experience. Lastly, using the simultaneity as a sample restriction, I document the existence of a split-ticket voting behaviour. In this regard, I find support for the divided government hypothesis as a mechanism.

Social capital and the power of mafia, with Francesca Calamunci

Abstract: What is the long-term effect of organised crime presence on social capital? This study combines multiple historical data sources, especially novel ones related to social capital and organised crime, to study this the relationship. Focusing on the expansion of criminal organisation in the Centre-North of Italy, we provide two alternative empirical identification strategies, based on an instrumental variable approach. First, we exploit a law ("soggiorno obbligato") that forced organised crime members living in the South of Italy to resettle in the Centre-North area. Second, we exploit the combination of migratory movements from the South to the Centre-North and the allocation of Marshall plan funds. Primarily employing a measure of tax compliance, which proxies for civic awareness, estimates show that long-term exposure to mafia presence depresses the social capital accumulation.

Green industrialization and local job multipliers, with Filippo Bontadini, Italo Colantone and Francesco Vona

Green Specialization and Labour Market Outcomes in EU Manufacturing Industries, with Filippo Bontadini and Francesco Vona

Organised Crime, Public Procurement and Firms, with Decio Coviello and Nicola Mastrorocco

Organised crime and human capital, within-city evidence from Italy

Awards and Fellowships

Economics Department Scholarship, Trinity College Dublin, 2018-2020 2020 Government of Ireland Postgraduate Scholarship, Irish Research Council, 2020-present

Interests

Sports, with a particular interest on basketball and football. Travelling, videogames and playing guitar.

References

Prof. Nicola Mastrorocco (PhD supervisor) Economics Department Trinity College Dublin n.mastrorocco@tcd.ie Prof. Gaia Narciso Economics Department Trinity College Dublin narcisog@tcd.ie Prof. Marvin Suesse Economics Department Trinity College Dublin marvin.suesse@tcd.ie

Last updated on April 4, 2023.